{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Walter Jarboe operated a gang of mercenaries in this state, kidnapping Yuki natives. Despite banning African American slavery, this state allowed for “apprenticing” of Native Americans in a form of slavery documented by John Ross Browne. In this state, Sheriff William Dixon massacred more than 150 Wintu people in the Bridge Gulch massacre. Slave labor in this state built New Helvetia, a fort owned by John Sutter. For ten points, name this state where many Native Americans were killed during an 1849 gold rush.",
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "question": "Privateer Henry Jennings attacked salvagers of this country’s ships that had sunk in a hurricane in 1715. A fleet of this country was captured by Piet Hein at the Bay of Matanzas, and George Rooke attacked this fleet at Vigo Bay in 1702. This country caused relatively high inflation in a namesake Price Revolution that was driven by trade of cochineal dye, silver from Callao, and other items regulated at its Casa de Contrataci´on. For ten points, name this European country that operated a treasure fleet of galleons between Manila and Acapulco.",
      "answer": "Spain"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s uncle of the same name and his brother Stesagoras each ruled the Chersonese as tyrants. Late in life, this man suffered a leg wound while attacking the island of Paros; he was imprisoned for treason and died of gangrene. This man, who was forced to fight the Scythians under Darius, convinced Athens to execute messengers sent by Darius demanding earth and water. The polemarch Callimachus broke a tie on the advice of this man, leading to a decisive victory in 490 BC. For ten points, name this general whose strategy won the Battle of Marathon.",
      "answer": "Miltiades the Younger"
    },
    {
      "question": "At the Dodan Barracks, a leader of this state named Philip Effiong gave a speech declaring its recognition of a rival nation’s government. The song “Land of the Rising Sun” was the official anthem of this state and was based on Jean Sibelius’ Finlandia. This state’s forces were defeated during the invasion of Port Harcourt. This state was centered on the city of Enugu and led by Colonel Ojukwu for the three years of its existence. For ten points, name this Igbo-majority state that broke from Nigeria in 1967.",
      "answer": "Biafra"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man rescued W.J. Walsh from drowning while posted on the Tonopah. Between 1949 and 1953, this man served as Plebiscite Administrator for Jammu and Kashmir. In Operation Galvanic, this man led the campaign to recapture the Gilbert Islands and he was made “Commander in Chief, Pacific Ocean Areas.” This admiral’s intelligence teams discovered a Japanese attack on Midway, leading to the destruction of four Japanese carriers. A class of nuclear aircraft carriers is named for, for ten points, what American World War II fleet admiral?",
      "answer": "Chester William Nimitz, Sr."
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s son Pufang is an advocate for disability rights, having been paralyzed during torture by the Red Guards. This man consolidated power with the help of the Eight Elders, who met frequently at his home. This man worked with Zhao Ziyang to remove Hua Guofeng from the premiership, noting that “it doesn’t matter whether a cat is white or black as long as it catches mice.” This man was criticized for suppressing the Tiananmen Square protests. Shanghai was opened to foreign investment by, for ten points, what Chinese leader who reformed the economy in the 1980s?",
      "answer": "Deng Xiaoping"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s daughter Mary played Kristin Shepard, who turned out to be the one who shot J.R. in the famous cliffhanger of the soap opera Dallas. This man, whose last TV appearance was on a Christmas special singing a duet with David Bowie, co-starred in a film series beginning with Road to Singapore with Bob Hope. A recording of this man was used in Operation Frequent Wind to signal the American evacuation from Saigon. For ten points, name this American actor and singer of “White Christmas.”",
      "answer": "Harold “Bing” Crosby"
    },
    {
      "question": "This general’s Philipsburg Proclamation offered fugitive slaves freedom upon joining the British Army. This general assumed his highest post after a large party known as the Mischianza was thrown for his predecessor. In an attempt to relieve Burgoyne, this man led the capture of Fort Montgomery and dismantled the Hudson River Chain. This man was succeeded by Guy Carleton in his highest post in 1782 after the defeat of General Cornwallis at the Battle of Yorktown. For ten points, name this Commander-in-Chief of British forces in North America after William Howe.",
      "answer": "Henry Clinton"
    },
    {
      "question": "This philosopher, who developed a method of steam distillation to produce rose water and essential oils, claimed he had read Aristotle’s Metaphysics 40 times before reading a commentary by al-Farabi. This main target of al-Ghazali’s The Incoherence of the Philosophers argued for the existence of the soul with the “floating man” argument. The Canon of Medicine and The Book of Healing were written by, for ten points, what Persian Islamic philosopher of the 11th century?",
      "answer": [
        "Avicenna or ibn Sina",
        "or Abu Ali Sina",
        "or Pur Sina"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Great Plank Road, or Canyon Road, was built to connect this city to the Tualatin Valley. Francis Pettygrove and Asa Lovejoy flipped a coin to decide the name of this city, whose suburbs include Clackamas and a town developed by ship workers Vanport. Henry Kaiser helped build Liberty Ships in this Pacific Northwest city, where early settlers described it as “Stumptown.” For ten points, name this former timber hub in Oregon that was named in honor of a city in Maine.",
      "answer": "Portland"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The division of this man’s empire between his sons alk-Amin and al-Ma’mun caused a civil war. Before becoming a ruler, this man led an assault against Empress Irene, reaching as far as Chrysopolis before turning around. Twelve mechanical knights were part of a water clock that this man sent to Charlemagne with an elephant and other gifts. This man, whose epithet means “Rightly Guided,” created the House of Wisdom in Baghdad, which became a center of learning during the Islamic Golden Age. For ten points, name this fifth Abbasid Caliph.",
        "answer": "Harun al-Rashid BONUS:AmongthescholarswhoworkedintheHouseofWisdomwasthisastronomerandmathematician whose Compendious Book on Calculation by Completion inspired the name of, and revolutionized, algebra. ANSWER: Muhammmad ibn Musa al-Khwarizmi 2 This leader’s reputation was hurt after attempting to cover up a leak of the military exercise Fallex 62. This leader declared “this is our breakthrough” after a new plan to pool coal production with France was adopted in the Schuman Declaration. More controversially, this politician ordered the arrest of Der Spiegel journalists in 1962 after they had leaked state secrets. Ludwig Erhard’s post-war economic revitalization took place under, for ten points, what first Chancellor of West Germany? ANSWER: Konrad Adenauer"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Adenauer promoted this doctrine of refusing to hold diplomatic relations with countries that recognized East Germany. This doctrine was followed between 1955 and 1970.",
        "answer": "Hallstein Doctrine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s popular education bill eventually led to the “common-school” system in Pennsylvania. Langdon Cheves was replaced by this man, who prepared Lewis and Clark’s expedition report for publication. After Louis McLane and William Duane refused to withdraw from an institution led by this man, Roger Taney was appointed Treasury Secretary. The Whigs’ support for this man and his institution was countered by Andrew Jackson, who refused to renew his charter. For ten points, name this final president of the Second Bank of the United States.",
        "answer": "Nicholas Biddle"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among Biddle’s supporters was this co-founder of the Second Bank who served as Minister to the UK and France after spending nearly 13 years as Secretary of the Treasury under Jefferson and Madison.",
        "answer": "Albert Gallatin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman asked a series of 42 questions about scripture in a letter she likely wrote from the Oratory of the Paraclete. A man named Fulbert was convinced that this woman could be tutored by a man who lusted after her; shortly thereafter, this woman gave birth to a son named Astrolabe, and Fulbert led a mob that castrated her tutor. Marriage and prostitution are compared in the writings of, for ten points, what 12th century French feminist writer who is most famous for her correspondences with the author of Sic et Non, Pierre Ab´elard?",
        "answer": "H´eloise d’Argenteuil"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The story of H´eloise inspired this immensely popular 1761 French epistolary novel. Its title character, described as “the new H´eloise,” is tutored by Saint Preux and marries Wolmar, a character based on the author’s patron, Baron d’Holbach.",
        "answer": [
          "Julie,",
          "the New Heloise"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A ruler of a kingdom in this modern country, Yalamber, had his head cut off by Lord Krishna according to the Mahabharata. The first two dynasties of this country were the Kirata and the Licchavi. Unification of this country occurred under Prithvi Narayan Shah, who conquered Nuwakot and created the Gorkha Kingdom. In 2001, Prince Diprendra killed 9 members of this country’s royal family. For ten points, name this Himalayan nation where pro-democracy protests took place in 2006 in Kathmandu.",
        "answer": "Nepal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man succeeded Birendra as the last king of Nepal. In 2006, he restored the parliament, which abolished the monarchy in 2008.",
        "answer": "Gyanendra Bir Bikram Shah Dev"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An artifact said to have belonged to this deity was chewed and spit out to create other deities. Another artifact was believed to have been hung from a tree to lure this deity from a cave; that mirror is believed to be held at the Grand Shrine of Ise [ee-say]. This goddess gave her grandson Ninigi the sword Kusanagi, one of the Imperial Regalia of Japan. The emperor of Japan traces his lineage to, for ten points, what sister of Susanoo, the Shinto sun goddess?",
        "answer": "Amaterasu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The legend that Japanese emperors are descended from Amaterasu is found in this 8th century AD compilation of myths, legends, and history. The more detailed Nihon Shoki was written shortly after this work, the oldest surviving Japanese text.",
        "answer": [
          "Kojiki",
          "Furukotofumi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was the subject of the case Al-Jundi vs. Mancusi, which ruled that Muslim victims had been singled out for abuse. During this event, negotiations between Russell Oswald and Elliot Barkley broke down, leaving hostages in the hands of Frank Smith. The killing of George Jackson in San Quentin inspired this event, which Governor Nelson Rockefeller was criticized for using deadly force to end. 33 people were killed fighting for better living conditions in, for ten points, what 1971 prison riot in New York?",
        "answer": "Attica prison riot"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In response to the Attica riot, members of this group tried to bomb the office of negotiator Russell Oswald. This group’s first riot, the 1969 “Days of Rage,” sought to “bring the war home” by, among other things, bombing the statue memorializing the police who died in the Haymarket riot.",
        "answer": "Weather Underground or the Weathermen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1832, this man’s bones were stolen and ritually incinerated. This man’s uncle Juan debated Cardinal Giuliano Cesarini at the Council of Florence. This man ordered condemned individuals to wear sanbenitos. Sixtus IV allowed the creation of a holy office led by this man, who created tribunals in Sevilla, Saragossa and C´ordoba. Despite being descended from conversos himself, this man targeted Jews and Muslims. The marraige of Ferdinand and Isabella was recommended by, for ten points, what royal advisor and leader of the Spanish Inquisition?",
        "answer": "Tom´as de Torquemada"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man, who arranged for a papal dispensation for Ferdinand and Isabella to marry, became Popein1492andsomewhattriedtocontroltheInquisitionbyappointingmilderassistantstoTorquemada.",
        "answer": [
          "Alexander VI",
          "Rodrigo Borgia"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Women’s Suffrage",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "US constitutional amendment that guarantees women’s suffrage.",
          "answer": "19th Amendment to the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who eventually supported suffrage as a key to winning World War I.",
          "answer": "Thomas Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffragette who was arrested for voting in 1872 and charged a $100 fine by Ward Hunt.",
          "answer": "Susan B. Anthony"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York city where that woman tried to vote.",
          "answer": "Rochester"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group led by Alice Paul that picketed the White House for suffrage; its members were tortured in prison.",
          "answer": "Silent Sentinels"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pacifist Montana representative who was the first woman in Congress.",
          "answer": "Jeannette Rankin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Populist Party chairwoman who was President of the WCTU for 20 years.",
          "answer": "Frances Willard"
        },
        {
          "question": "1875 Supreme Court case that ended the “new departure” strategy by ruling the Constitution didn’t give anyone the right to vote.",
          "answer": "Minor v. Happersett"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Contemporaries of Stalin",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Man who preceded Stalin as leader of the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "Vladimir Lenin or Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rival who was executed by Ramon Mercader in Mexico in 1940.",
          "answer": [
            "Leon Trotsky",
            "Lev Davidovich Bronstein"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Yugoslavian president who told Stalin “Stop sending people to kill me” after their ideological split.",
          "answer": [
            "Josip Broz Tito",
            "either",
            "both names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German Field Marshall, captured at Stalingrad, who Stalin refused to trade for his own captured son.",
          "answer": "Friedrich Paulus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary who supposedly wrote a 1924 letter to British communists and was executed in a show trial in 1936.",
          "answer": [
            "Grigory Zinoviev",
            "Hirsch Apfelbaum"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician whose 1934 murder at the Smolny Institute was probably ordered by Stalin and definitely led to the Great Purge.",
          "answer": [
            "Sergei Kirov",
            "Sergei Kostrikov"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Head of the NKVD who became First Deputy Premier after Stalin’s death but was ousted and executed in 1953.",
          "answer": "Lavrentiy Beria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Editor of Pravda and theorist of “socialism in one country” who was executed after the last Moscow Show Trial.",
          "answer": "Nikolay Bukharin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Peru",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Peru, where a 1996 embassy hostage crisis took place.",
          "answer": "Lima"
        },
        {
          "question": "Culture whose people created massive line drawings in the Peruvian desert soil.",
          "answer": [
            "Nazca people",
            "Nazca Lines"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician of Japanese descent who served as a corrupt president during the 1990s.",
          "answer": "Alberto Fujimori"
        },
        {
          "question": "Winner of the 2010 Nobel Prize in Literature, who lost the 1990 presidential election.",
          "answer": "Mario Vargas Llosa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Communist guerrilla group that was fought by the government death squad Grupo Colina.",
          "answer": [
            "Communist Party of Peru - Shining Path",
            "Sendero Luminoso"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of that group; he was captured in 1992.",
          "answer": "Abimael Guzman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last Sapa Inca, who was executed in 1572; an independence fighter in the 18th century and another guerrilla group took his name.",
          "answer": [
            "Tupac Amaru",
            "Jose Gabriel Tupac Amaru",
            "Tupac Amaru II",
            "Tupac Amaru Revolutionary Movement"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Event being celebrated by the hostages when the embassy crisis began on December 17, 1996.",
          "answer": "Emperor Akihito’s birthday"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was removed from his post of Lord High Admiral after going missing with a fleet of ships for ten days. This ruler was the last king to appoint a Prime Minister against Parliament’s wishes. This man outlawed (20 pts)",
        "child labor under the Factory Act and abolished slavery in most of the empire, but is more known for a bill that (10 pts)",
        "eliminated “rotten boroughs” and greatly increased the voting population. The 1832 Great Reform Act was overseen by, for ten points, what final king of the House of Hanover, the uncle of Queen Victoria?"
      ],
      "answer": "William IV"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Senator Olin D. Johnston declined to attend this event, noting “criminal, fanatical, and communist elements” would attend. Prisoners were moved to different prisons before this event because police believed there would be mass arrests. Before this event, Walter Fauntroy threatened “Do you want a fight here tomorrow?” after a $16,000 (20 pts)",
        "sound system was sabotaged. Josephine Baker gave an opening address and the “Queen of Gospel,” (10 pts)",
        "Mahalia Jackson, performed at this event. A. Philip Randolph and Bayard Rustin organized, for ten points, what event calling for “Jobs and Freedom” for African-Americans, at which Martin Luther King Jr. gave the “I Have A Dream” speech?"
      ],
      "answer": "1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist painted a full-length portrait of Muhammad Dervish Khan, an ambassador sent by Tipu Sultan to France. This artist indicated the recent death of a child named Sophie with an empty bassinet draped with a black cloth held back by (20 pts)",
        "Dauphin Louis Joseph. In that painting, this artist’s patron wears a red dress in an attempt to repair the (10 pts)",
        "reputation that had been damaged by a painting of this artist’s patron wearing a blue-feathered straw hat and a striped gold sash over a scandalously informal white gown. For ten points, name this court painter for Marie Antoinette."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "E´lisabeth Louise Vige´e Le Brun",
        "Madame Le Brun"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roland Osterweis described this belief as a “landscape dotted with figures drawn mainly out of the past.” Moses Jacob Ezekiel’s sculptures promoted this belief, which was popularized by Jubal (20 pts)",
        "Early. This theory is employed by a Thomas Dixon novel whose film adaptation was screened in the White House by Woodrow Wilson, (10 pts)",
        "D.W. Griffith’s The Birth of a Nation. Reconstruction is condemned in, for ten points, what ideology that romanticizes the Confederacy as heroic defenders of the South whose loss was inevitable due to Northern industrial advantages?"
      ],
      "answer": "Lost Cause of the Confederacy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After Lord Dufferin offered to create a “free state” in this province, many Icelandic Mormons traveled to its colony of New Iceland. Due to incorrect metric conversions, an Air Canada flight had to land in this province’s town of (20 pts)",
        "Gimli. Thomas Greenway and Wilfrid Laurier defused a 19th century crisis over religion and language in this province’s schools. Premier Duff Roblin had to build a floodway in this province after the (10 pts)",
        "Red River of the North overflowed. For ten points, name this Canadian province where, in 1919, a general strike disrupted Winnipeg."
      ],
      "answer": "Manitoba"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler of these people legendarily planted a black poplar to announce that he would take the throne. One ruler of these people accidentally shot Saint Giles with an arrow. Wamba led these people, who were governed by the Code of Leovigild and the earlier Code of (20 pts)",
        "Euric. Another leader of these people died when he fought Tariq ibn Ziyad of the Ummayads at the Battle of Guadalete; that man was (10 pts)",
        "Roderic. These people held several councils of Toledo under kings like Reccared I. For ten points, name these Gothic rulers of what is now Spain, contrasted with the eastern Ostrogoths."
      ],
      "answer": "Visigoths"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this battle, the sword of the recently-killed Prince Imperial Napoleon was offered in a rejected peace treaty. This battle began with an attempt to cross the Mbilane River by Evelyn Wood’s flying column and Redvers Buller’s cavalry. The losing side in this battle was subsequently (20 pts)",
        "divided into 13 chiefdoms by Garnet Wolseley, who had arrived too late to take command. The royal kraal of (10 pts)",
        "Cetshwayo was burned in this battle, which Lord Chelmsford hastily initiated in an attempt to salvage his reputation from a prior defeat at Isandlwana. For ten points, name this 1879 battle for the Zulu capital."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Ulundi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1886, riots in this city occurred after police tried to control a crowd watching illegal eel-pulling. A silent walk in this city commemorates an event in which sacramental bread was put in a fire but remained intact. Protestant control of this city began after the 1578 (20 pts)",
        "Alteratie. In 2004, filmmaker Theo van Gogh was assassinated in this city, where a (10 pts)",
        "dike was built in the 1930s to change the Zuider Zee into a freshwater lake. Three concentric canals encircle, for ten points, what city where Anne Frank’s family was betrayed to the Nazis, the capital of the Netherlands?"
      ],
      "answer": "Amsterdam"
    }
  ]
}